hello and
welcome this is actin guest stream
number
87.2 on September 10th 2024 we're
continuing on with the cogar ecosystem
series with John Bo so John thank you
again go for it and we'll look forward
to people's comments and
questions great thank you Daniel
uh my name is John Bo I'm a active
inference Institute research fellow um I
have two new papers published or excuse
me posted as preprints and um that's
what this live stream these two live
streams are about next slide please
Daniel so on September 5th we had our
first one I encourage uh listeners to
check that out the links are in the uh
PDF and today we're talking about the
second paper which is uh the cogar
ecosystem preliminary thoughts on a
story graph meaning
representation uh next slide
please so the the uh next several slides
are Rec uh brief Recaps of what we
discussed before uh this the cogar
project is new and it's large and it's
fairly complex and um it might help a
little bit to set the stage for this
talk just by review quickly reviewing
some of the main uh components of the
cogar system so cogar means cognitive
narrative and it's it's a it's a it's a
um the cogar system is still a concept
it's it's new it's very much being
created as we
speak um it's conceived to be an
open-source on online ecosystem of tools
and services Etc
that facilitates group cognition
especially for large groups and
especially with regard to um
deliberation strategizing and Collective
problem problem
solving uh cogar helps users in the
phrase I like to use is tell their story
so um I use the word story and I use the
word narrative and in in the paper and I
will in this talk but I don't I don't
mean story as in Fable
or uh I mean story as in actually what I
mean by story is is the a belief model
of a user so the idea is that relative
to some problem or situation of Interest
a group is having a online discussion
you could say and the users are
contributing
their an externalization of their belief
model to this discussion so they are
they are in this in in this story
they're they're describing what's the
situation or problem what happened why
did it happen What might happen next uh
what what might happen next clearly is
predictive right so there's predictions
are part of a generally are part of a
story who does this situation affect who
was involved what does it mean what
should be done what can be learned all
those kinds of questions uh are are can
be addressed in a story and a story
really is a a model an externalization
of beliefs about how a user sees the
world and sees the situation and thinks
that the world
Works um next slide
please um so uh stories can be rich and
by Rich I mean potentially long complex
nuanced informative conditional Dynamic
Etc so maybe a typical story might be
the equivalent of a few pages of text
perhaps but but could be even be longer
could be like a equivalent to a book
chapter for example or a story could be
very short equivalent to a paragraph
that really depends on what the user
wants to communicate but they can be
rich um and this is much different from
other uh online services that are aimed
at collaborative decision- making and
and similar similar tasks
this is not a um this is not the a you
know choose multiple choice sort of uh
uh system you know where you where the
user can contribute to the conversation
by choosing A B C or D or filling in a
blank with a couple of words this this
stories can be much much richer richer
than
that uh there is a back-end
computational system and that system uh
assists and guides users in constructing
their stories
um uh assess the stories for quality but
for example is the story on topic is it
comprehensible did did did the user
follow whatever rules the group set out
for submitting stories um and primarily
the backend computational systems helps
a user to D helps the group to digest
and make sense of the many stories that
might have been submitted and when I say
many stories and group and and large
group I mean potentially a group of of
thousands to tens of thousands to
hundreds of thousands even to millions
of peoples so
um you know potentially very very large
groups um and the backend system also
performs inference for for queries that
users generates for example I'm part of
a group we're all sharing our stories
and I might have some question about
some some particular story like did does
does that in that story
does the economy um you know are there
does U unemployment go down you know
some question like that and I can pose a
query or even a more specific query to
to the either to the Storyteller of that
story or to the story itself and the
system can also generate uh queries all
by itself the system might ask when
you're creating a story the system might
ask you I'm I'm confused do you mean
that the uh unemployment is going to go
down because of this or you know some
some such question like
that but the system this is quite uh
important the system does not predict
the future so it's not going to assess a
story for how useful that will be in
real life or how accurate it will be um
that's the purpose of a story a user
does this in their story the user says I
believe that if we take actions a b c
and d then unemployment will um go down
for example
and uh the system does also not assess
the realism or accuracy in of a story or
a group of stories and that's really uh
the responsibility of the group that's
that's that's collecting the
stories uh next slide
please importantly those last two
bullets means that the the the system
the backend system does not have to have
its own model of
how the world Works in reality like um
it does not need to know Mechanics for
example or biology it just it really
just needs to communicate stories and
help users digest stories and help users
create stories in such a way that users
can communicate their belief systems and
share their belief systems
together so if the purpose of uh the
cogar system is to facilitate group
cognition you know obvious question is
well what is cognition
and in this project I'm looking at
cognition through the active inference
lens and active inference is a normative
basian description of cognition there in
the previous PDFs for the first series
there's links that users that listeners
could follow to find some literature on
this and obviously there's references in
my papers
also uh so and uh an agent has in in
active inference an agent has an
internal probabilistic model about how
the world works and that is the model
that is conveyed really that is
externalized Into The
Story So cognition is uh idealized here
simplified as a four-part cyclic process
of predict act sense and learn so I I
underlined the word act here because
often that's really not considered a
part of cognition but in the active
inference uh world it is so um for
example I'm I'm learning how to play
football I predict that if I jump up
high and and raise my arms I might catch
a high pass I I act on those predictions
I sense whether I actually caught the
ball or not and if I and if I didn't
catch the ball I learn from my mistakes
I learn that I need to jump higher or
reach higher or or do some take some
other action and then we would repeat
the process and over time I I get better
and better at catching that
ball um and an an in action an agent
favor choices that ensure the greatest
resolution of uncertainty under the
constraint that's constraints that are
preferred outcomes are realized so my
pref my preferences are that I catch
that ball and I really want to reduce
the uncertainty that I'm going to miss
it so I repeat this learning process
over and over and my certainty about
catching that ball goes up and up as I
get better
um
and active inference uh
is it's normative so it offers a
description of offers a description of
functional cognition and that's what
we're after in the cogar system is to
facilitate functional cognition as
opposed to dysfunctional cognition so
for
example dysfunctional cognition would
would not ensure the greatest resolution
of uncertainty under the constraints
that preferred outcomes are realize that
would be the that would if if if
uncertainty does not decrease about
preferred outcomes then that's a sign
that that uh cognition is is is you know
may have
problems um next slide
please so what is kogar really then um I
in in this project I I look at a group
as an organism as a cognitive
organism so just like any organism it
needs to needs to react in the world it
needs to do those that four-step process
of you know sense act
learn uh a cognitive
architecture uh integrates information
and coordinates action and every
organism has a cognitive architecture
and so do groups so do groups viewed as
organisms and the cognitive architecture
for an individual human say is the human
biology central nervous system the body
and also uh tools that a human might use
uh computers for example could be
considered a part of that cognitive
architecture notes to remember is an
extension of the brain's capacity to
remember for
example and the cognitive architecture
for a group it might include rules
methods institutions
sensors uh you know sensors for air
pollution for example for a group that
might be a
nation and essentially all the
components by which and through which
cognition occurs as an aside in a
previous series of paper three series of
three papers that we discussed in a
previous um uh guest streams a few years
ago I I look at a society's core systems
that is governance systems uh economic
systems Financial systems legal systems
as part of that society's cognitive
architecture
and this cogar project is is kind of a a
closely related or maybe you could say
an offshoot of that initial
series um so cogar is a component of the
cognitive architecture of the groups
that use it and its purpose again is to
facilitate facilitate functional
cognition and I and as I've mentioned a
story is a potentially Dynamic
externalized reput representation of a
user's internal belief model about the
how the World
works next
slide just a couple more of these Recaps
and then we're on to the meat of today's
talk um so um under the hood this is how
the cogar system works um I've used the
word story I've used the word narrative
but um I do not mean textual uh
information so it's not users don't
convey and discuss and and share their
stories in in text form but rather in a
very special kind of meaning
representation that I call a story
graph um and story graphs really are the
core innovation of the cogar system it's
it's really
what uh allows the cogar system to
function
well um this diagram shows how story
graphs are constructed a user might
either speak or write uh short text
passages in a sentence a few sentences
maybe with some metadata associated with
that perhaps a table perhaps a graph you
know something like that perhaps a a few
words about how the sentence is supposed
to be
interpreted um uh the system accepts
that uh those passages uh translates
that into a a story graph fragment and
then merges that story graph fragment
into the growing story graph and the
story graph fragment and the story graph
that's that's that's the meaning
representation uh for the cogar
system once the story graph is
constructed then several things can
happen it could be translated into a
natural language potentially so uh one
day you should be able to you know
instruct the system to take the story
graph and then read it back to me you
know play it back to me so I can hear
how
sounds uh or translate that story graph
into some other alternative meaning
representation that's may be better
suited for a particular logical or
inference some kind of inference model
or some kind of analysis or translate it
directly into you know either in part or
in whole into some kind of probabilistic
model or logical model or other kind of
model to conduct uh either analysis or
inference next slide please
here's an example of a meaning
representation that's used this is a
very popular uh uh meaning
representation called abstract meaning
representation this is for the sentence
a similar technique is almost always is
almost impossible to apply to other
crops such as cotton soybeans and rice
uh you can you know you can see at a
glance from this meaning representation
that it's graph based that's one thing
and that the edges in this graph
represent some kind of relationship
between words and the
sentence the the rest of it is not
important and I don't you we don't use
uh AMR in the cogar system we're
actually the the the purpose of this
second paper and is to is to explore
what is the best meaning representation
for
cogar um what does what should it do
what should it how should it be
constructed what should it be able to
accomplish those kinds of
questions but this gives you a this this
graphical this graph picture gives you a
very rough idea of of what we might be
after next slide
please so um the purpose of the of the
story graph meaning representation is to
represent a story in a format that's
less ambiguous the natural language
natural language can be very
ambiguous and uh it should be a
representation that is readable and
understandable both by humans and
computers as a as a creator of a story I
should be able to look at that at that
graph and and confirm or validate that
yes that the system
understood what I was trying to tell it
you know things like that it provides a
structure for inference and Analysis it
it it serves as a
showed in the previous slide it serves
as input to various kinds of inference
and analytical models and it serves as
an
interlingua which is a a natural
language independent representation
that's suitable for translation into
other languages and and
models next
slide so now we now we can really begin
with today's
talk so what is the cogar meaning
representation that's the question but
whatever it is it's fit it's fit for
purpose and what does fit for purpose
mean Daniel if you back up one
slide this is the purpose so the task at
hand is to is to uh design a meaning
representation
that that is capable of performing in
these tasks okay not let's go forward
two
slides all right so um I've already
showed you a an example of AMR abstract
meaning
representation um and I've mentioned
that that's a common uh meaning
representation used in in um in research
so uh there's others so before we before
we jump into you know questions about
what should the
cogn um meaning representation look like
it's useful to look at the meaning
representations that are used in the
research World particularly in natural
language
inference and natural language
inferences inferences falls under the
general category of natural language
processing um there's many tasks that
that fall into the categories of NLP and
uh nlu natural language understanding uh
and natural language inference is one of
them and perhaps it's uh n is the in a
sense the most difficult because in in
in
nli for inference this the the system or
the model really needs to understand the
meaning of some text so this is the this
is the way that n is conducted uh in re
in the research study
uh some text is selected usually that
text is just a single sentence or maybe
you know short a small number of
sentences at the
most um and that text might be selected
from some some database of of sentences
you know where the meaning is is well
understood and that text then is sent to
a natural language processing system so
for for parsing word sens
dis ambiguation
um the result of that is then sent to
some meaning representation such as AMR
and then the the meaning representation
is used within the inference method so
this is um this is typically how it's
done but it
cogar the the cogar is is much different
this the setting is much different in
cogar numbers one two and three here
happen almost at the same time so and
it's and it's interactive so uh cognit
doesn't select text out of a database to
make a story it users are are
contributing text to make a story and
they're doing that for some reason they
want to they want to a user wants to
convey some information that some aspect
of their beliefs about how the world
works so
um so in in a in a nli study that text
is fixed it it you know you
you you're given a sentence and then the
whole system is going to be scored on
how well it understands that particular
sentence but uh in cogar if the system
doesn't understand what you try to say
it can it can ask you for feedback it
can say I don't understand who who is
the word he referring to for example or
do you mean flame do you mean flame as
in a hot uh burning candle or do you
mean flame as in uh you know a ro a
romantic interest so the system can ask
you for ask you questions give you
feedback uh maybe suggest phrasing or or
just simply say I don't understand what
you what you just entered and then the
user is able to adjust that text to
something that the system can
understand uh which of course can reduce
ambiguity and error and uh and you know
improve the quality of the story that
the text that is being converted into a
story um and uh and as I showed in one
of the graphs a few slides ago the
system then takes that text and and
converts that into a story graph
fragment and and uh depending on the use
case for the cogar system say in the in
a use case that involves group decision
making
um the editing of that story might occur
in over a series of rounds where people
edit their stories share their stories
the system helps digest the set of
stories in a given round and what you
know how they've changed and what they
entail and you know how they're
different and how they're similar and um
then at the end of each round users
would have the opportunity maybe to read
other people's stories digest the
information from other stories and maybe
change their story if they see an idea
that they like or they think oh that's I
should have included that I meant to but
I didn't and I'm going to include that
in my story now so in that process of
iteration in rounds the quality of the
story increases even further so that's
that's really quite different from the
research setting that is typically used
in nli and it gives the cogar system a
lot more flexibility as to how it
operates it because it can interact with
the user and ask questions and get
feedback you know give feedback to the
user uh and tell the user that it
doesn't understand something when it
doesn't understand something um it
really has the capacity at least in you
know the potential capacity to create
much uh higher quality uh
stories uh and and perform even more
complex forms of inference than would be
possible in normal nli
studies okay next slide
so in the literature over the years many
uh meaning representations have been
proposed this is this this is a table
from the second article but there's even
more than this this is just a some
selected meaning representations and
actually u meaning representations are
being developed and created uh regularly
so it's it's not that there's three
fixed meaning representations and you
have to pick one of them that's not
really the way it works people are
creating new ones
as as new situations arises new tasks
arises that they're trying to
address um we will focus uh on a few of
them today and the and the second paper
focuses on a few of them uh particularly
discourse representation uh Theory um U
which is I don't know about the fifth
one down or so and um uh there's a few
others type Theory with records the last
one and we'll also look at discos Circ
towards the bottom there which is not
exactly a meaning representation but
it's
related next
slide this is a t this is a uh graphic
from Lou
2021 and uh he was interested in in
meaning representations for document
length text and so are we you know
document length text means you know
potentially the the equivalent of a a
book or a book chapter for
example um so we have the same interest
as Lou uh he's also interested in
graphical meaning representations not
all meaning representations are
graphical and the reason that you might
prefer a graphical meaning
representation is because graphs
computers understand graphs very well
that's a it's a way to encode uh
information such that computers are able
to process it well and I might I might
back up just a minute here and say like
why you know why why is it even
necessary that a that a backend
computational system uh assesses stories
and and and and you
know does inference on stories why not
just why not just write your story in
text form and and you know share it with
the group why why not that well the
reason is because
uh we're interested here in group in uh
group cognition in the large group
setting so if if you have a group of say
a 100,000 people and each of them is
submitting some long story that's
complicated and and nuanced and um you
know dynamic that they're going to
change it you know maybe in a next week
as they learn something
new there's no human that's able to
digest you know 100, long stories it's
just not going to happen so the the
purpose of that backend system is to
help use help the group to digest all of
that information and make sense of all
that
information and that's why uh the
computer needs to understand what is
written and that is one one way to do
that is to use a graph-based meaning
representation so uh in L's table you
can see that discourse representation
Theory really scores quite well you know
for all the many things that are
necessary for understanding U you know
aspects of te
text and um and for the very same
reasons uh you know DRT is is uh looks
interesting for the cogn our system
also next slide
please so this is an example of
discourse representation Theory it's
it's this is the Box form and DRT is not
not graph based inherently graph-based
but people have proposed ways to convert
this into a graph this is a DRT for the
two sentences Max fell John might have
pushed him uh we have some reference
reference X1
X2
uh X1 is a a person named
Max uh and some event happens he fell
and um he fell before some event uh and
and the that event being being pushed by
Bush by John and the the two boxes
represent you know roughly the two
sentences and they're related in the
sense that this word because because of
K1
K2 yeah Max fell because John might have
pushed him um
uh yeah that's that's that I think it's
it's kind of straightforward how you
would read a a DRT
box next slide
please as I said DRT itself is not
necessarily not inherently graph-based
and Lou came up with a version of DRT
that he calls discourse representation
tree structure tree structure
brts that is uh that is graph-based and
that really is uh is aimed at document
length length text and uh this looks
particularly interesting you know in the
cogar setting because you know it's
graph-based it's it's it's really
constructed for long text and it has all
the benefits that uh that DRT
has so you could imagine a a story graph
looking a little bit like this but still
um far more
sophisticated um next slide
please that by the way that was a that
was a um drts for the very same two
sentences Maxell John might have pushed
him another another T this is not really
a meaning representation per se but
closely related something that would be
of interest in the cogar setting is type
Theory with records so um type Theory
actually is is closer closely related to
category Theory uh types are really like
category
objects and um in type type Theory type
Theory with records is a hybrid type
Theory but in type Theory with records
there's
records uh that is you know in a sense a
abstract description of some potential
situation the potential situation here
is uh a boy hugs a dog that's that's the
event that is this hypothetical that
could happen boy hugs a dog and for that
to happen there has to be a boy there
has to be a dog and there has to be some
event where the boy hugs the dog so
that's written as a
record and um then there has to be uh um
if that event is perceived in Life or in
a story or in in the imagination there
has to there there becomes a witness for
that event so type the records has both
record types and
Witnesses and a witness really is like a
proof and the proof the proof of this
boy hugs dog event is that uh you know I
witnessed a boy and I witnessed a dog
and I witnessed this boy hugging the dog
so there we go that's the
proof and uh this is actually uh type
theth records really kind of captures in
a in a way the the way human cognition
works um because I we have in our minds
these kind of Poss possible things that
could happen and then we witness the
world uh and and process our s sense
information and we usually make then
probabilistic judgments about whether
something happened uh it's dark I think
that was a horse in the front yard it
looked like a horse it was big it
sounded like a horse I don't know why a
horse should be in my front yard but I
think I'm pretty sure that was a horse
so that would be a potential witness for
a horse in the yard type
event uh TTR is very flexible uh Records
can be nested it can be as complex as
you would like uh you know it's it's
kind of closely related to DRT but it
can do some things and has some
capabilities that maybe DRT doesn't have
uh and it's inference using type th
records is potentially fast uh in that
it's depends mostly on type checking so
you know was there a boy you know a
individual of type boy was there a dog
uh and so on and because it depends
mostly on type checking it should play
well with proof assistance for which
there's um you know um sophisticated um
um software programs to do that Serv as
proof assistance logical proof
assistance so inference with TTR could
be potentially fast and as I said it
mimics human cognition more so than
interpretation of logical formulas it's
more flexible than
that next
slide so what what I'm doing here maybe
I should have introduced what I'm doing
a little bit but I'm just going through
some of the some of the uh you know kind
of um meaning representations that that
look uh you know potentially useful for
the cogar setting
so I'm going to take a a a quick
diversion from that though we'll get
back to it uh I'm going to take a quick
diversion and talk about large language
models in this
setting um I think you know probably
most users are familiar now with long uh
large language models in the paper I
call them pre-ra pre-trained language
models but large they're large in the
sense that have billions of of of
parameters as the top graph is showing
and the the number the size of the
models is increasing over the years so
they they essentially ingest an enormous
amount of text that's
available via the web and other sources
and then process that text and find find
associations between words between words
and and between words in a sentence and
between words in different sentences and
things like that so that U through those
ass you know it learns those
associations and then
can perform various tasks based on based
on the information in those
associations and um the large language
models typically use some kind of
Transformer attention mechanism which
showed in the you know high level view
is shown in the bottom graph there
there's a some text comes in at the
bottom this is a French a few French
words and uh that's encoded through an
encoder that information is sent to the
decoder uh there's attention mechanisms
mixed in there and then the output of
the decoder is is going to be some U
some you know answer to a query and in
this sense in this in this case it's the
um translation of the French into
English uh I won't go into any you know
it's not necessary to go into any more
detail about how Transformers and large
language model works but that's the high
level
overview um uh next
slide and the reason that I'm injecting
this llm discussion here is that I
really wanted to talk about Vector
edding because that'll be important to
the next meaning representation we talk
about so um you know in using large
language models um words are
converted embedded really into Vector
vectors to capture their meaning so
um this is just a really simple sort of
example but suppose you have the word
cat and suppose you have a list of u a v
a vector really a list Vector of of 30
other words like Mom and dog and tree
and R run and you know a variety of
other
words well cat is going to be more
similar to the the meaning of cat is
going to be more similar to some of
those and less similar to others so cat
might be very similar to Tiger so if
tiger is in this uh is one of the
possibilities in this in this list then
that's going to get a high similarity
score so from that process you could
imagine constructing a series of numbers
that are reflecting how similar some uh
query object is to some reference
objects or at least reference vectors so
that's basically how uh word words are
the meaning of words is embedded into
vectors and then these vectors can be
used in a variety of you know of comput
computational tasks um it also opens up
the possibility for what's called a
vector database
where on the left there the there at the
bottom left the user has some kind of
query for example how do you translate
this sentence into from French into
English maybe has some extra content uh
that you know that's that kind of gives
more information about the setting so
maybe maybe the content in this example
is a the French phrase has to do with
the petroleum industry for example it's
like a little hint as to you know little
hint as to what this phrase might mean
those uh you know that information then
is in embedded in vectors and those
vectors could be saved in a vector
database very large Vector database and
then at the bottom right um the the llm
could communicate back and forth with
the vector database looking for uh
vectors that are good matches for uh
what the query is and then eventually
the llm llm spits out some kind of
answer uh so that's brief overview of
vector embedding and that'll be
important in the next meaning
representation we discuss next slide
please now I I'm calling the Disco here
a meaning representation but that's not
actually true that's that's it it's it's
not a formal meaning representation it's
really more a computational
method uh so uh discos distributional
compositional circuits is kind of a
mixture of category Theory and dist
distributional SM semantics dist
distributional semantics is really what
I was just referring to referring to
with a vector embedding of word
meaning and it presents a a graphical
calculus via string diagrams an example
of a string diagram is shown there and
this is not just a uh a diagram that
sort of shows relationships it's
actually a computational diagram it's
the way the the the way string diagrams
are processed really implies that
there's
some computational aspect going on
here so let's just look at the uh at the
very top left there we have some entity
Alice and Alice is
sober and the meaning of Alice and the
meaning of
sober should be merged in some way to
create the concept of a sober Alice
right and how is that merging done well
it's depicted as a string uh uh string
diagram is shown here but the the vector
representations of Alice and sober are
then multiplied uh you know you can
think another word for vectors or
complicated vectors is tensors so the
tensors might be very high
dimensional and then you have some
multiplication multiplication happening
in in a high-dimensional space and that
is merging the ideas of Alice and sober
and then it continues on through the
rest of the graph uh multiplication of
high dimensional tensors and then the
answer is whatever the you know the
output of the last um um tensor
product uh
U the the last event and that tensor
product line of
events so um just a little bit I don't
want to really get into category Theory
too much but it OB category Theory
obviously is important in this sort of
approach and um and as we'll discuss
later it has category theory in applied
category Theory really may be applicable
in many of the many of the computational
tasks uh that uh that cogn has to
perform so I'll just say a few quick
words on it uh so D string diagrams
represent morphisms and mon monal
categories uh uh category objects are
the nouns the strings so the string for
Alice is a that's a object and uh morph
the boxes are morphisms morphisms are
like Maps like functions sort
of and they transform one type into
another so we have the type Alice and we
have the types over and then we're going
to do something to merge those two types
together um and then funs map the um mon
monal category of string diagrams into
another category vector vector of vector
spaces and that's where this
multiplication uh linear Maps can happen
multiplication so uh again this string
diagram is really a computational
diagram more than anything else
and the other thing maybe is important
here is that um since these are since
we're talking about um U you know linear
multiplic multiplication operations in
high-dimensional space um this system
becomes a little it's really really best
suited maybe for U quantum computers
quantum computers could handle the you
know when they're when as they become
more and more available and as they
improve quantum computers could handle
this kind of situation very very well it
can still be done on on on you know
current systems but uh would really be
ideally suited for Quantum um
computation next slide
please so there's variations on Disco
Circ uh actually on Disco cat uh which
is the the the ver discos Circ is really
aimed at understanding um you know how
multiple sentences fit together disco
cat is aimed at understanding single
sentences uh so a higher order version
of disco cat uh
as
uh uses Lambda calculus as
as a word in this higher order version
is a diagram valued higher order
function via Lambda calculus and then
the meaning of a sentence can be given
by composing Lambda terms together and
then that ends up with a diagram that
can be interpretated interpreted in the
category vect as in discocat so the the
this is again a computational graph that
we're looking at it's for the sentence
no man is an island and the uh Pink
areas in there that is the areas where
um the actual Vector multiplication is
happening but because it's offering this
higher order uh function uh uh it can it
can do things that discusser can't do it
can easily handle adverbs propositions
negation quantifiers and more so um this
is really interesting uh it has
potential uh it it may offer a way to
use the system that is um less
that is more applicable to Conventional
Computing rather than Quantum
Computing and um it's you know obviously
more flexible and can convey can can
process meaning you know new other kinds
of meanings that disco cir has trouble
with um but um it's new and it it this
higher order version there's not a
higher order version of disco cir yet
this is a higher order version for disco
cat nevertheless quite
interesting next slide
please um okay so so we now I'm going to
jump back and and talk a little bit
about the potential roles of large
language models in cogar but just to
kind of summarize what we've already
discussed we've talked about a couple of
U of of meaning representations or
things like disco Circ and higher order
disco cat that are Clos closely related
so we have a few ideas now about maybe
what a um a cogar meaning representation
might look like it's probably going to
be graph-based it might look like it
lose uh you know tree
structures
uh potential for um you know especially
with quantum computers potential for
kind of using in a very different
approach of U of the Disco cat and
higher order disco Circ when it's
available so that we have a few ideas
that we might work from and now the
question arises well
why why do why were you even want to use
a meaning representation why can't you
just take text you know some sentences
and feed that into a large language
model and and get the kind of inference
that you seek do the kinds of analysis
that you seek so I want to address that
question
um uh
so large language models you know
they're pretty amazing they can do a lot
of things and they've really in in a you
know in a sense taken the research World
by a storm in the last few years and
they've been used in nli so there's a
numerous studies that have used a large
language models to perform a variety of
nli tasks and there's many nli tasks and
and different databases and you know
complexities of sentences and uh types
of you know of of
linguistic phenomena that are used in
for various kinds of nli tests in
various kinds of nli
tests so um from from everything that's
been written so far that I've that I've
digested um
llms can be amazing but they can also
really struggle in certain situations
and it happens that that's some of those
situations are the situations of cogn so
llm struggle with complex text uh long
text uh if it's not domain specific they
can struggle uh you know stories can be
about anything they can be about
industrial processes or environmental
issues or social issues or political
issues or whatever you know story can be
about
anything um uh and llm struggle with
that kind of variable uh you know
setting variable domains and also
struggle regarding logical reason
reasoning especially over long texts and
uh in some uh uh nli t uh tests llms can
really do quite poorly you know some
they do okay and some they can really
fail LM llms can also hallucinate they
can kind of make up make up people and
situations and and uh they don't they
don't generally this I'm really talking
about vanilla llms here but they
generally don't provide explainable
answers and that's kind of important
because for example I'm writing a story
and the and um maybe the
system scores my story quality in some
way maybe I get a low a low score for
story quality because perhaps the story
is off you know in theory perhaps the
story is off top IPC or it's uh not just
not comprehensible or it's incomplete or
you know some kind of problem like that
and I maybe want to know why why is why
am I getting a low quality score in the
story what's what's going on why did you
give me this score and in general at
least a vanilla llm wouldn't be able to
provide that answer would its answer
would be well I multiplied all these
numbers in some high-dimensional space
and came up with this value and that's
why you got that's why you got a low
score uh and in contrast to that um this
is just one of many contrasts uh using a
story graph as an intermediary in the
computational process uh provides you
know several utilities one of which is
that that story graph can then be
inspected visually by a user to see if
the system has understood the story
correctly I can if I'm as I'm creating a
story I can view aspects of the staph to
see that um that you know these two
persons in the story are related one
works for the other for example the
system understood that
correctly um so uh you know the question
here is it's not whether llms should be
used at all in cogar it's really more
the question of um there's two
approaches uh an approach to natural
language inference that does not use any
kind of intermediate meaning
representation just just text as input
and the approach where uh there is a
intermediate meaning representation in
this case a story graph and uh from what
I can
tell um in reading the literature the
llms are just not capable of doing all
the things all the sort of inference and
analytical processes that would be
necessary um in the cogar setting so
using story graphs as an intermediary in
that computational process could be uh I
think more useful and and also keep in
mind that suppose that the group is very
large suppose that hundreds of thousands
of people are are gathering for some
some event to you know explore some
situation um and and many of them are
submitting long stories long complex
stories well you know that you would
have to somehow compare all these
stories to each other you'd have to have
llms ingesting very large masses of
textual information and then comparing
their various you know parts parts and
uh you know LL and then following The
Logical line of reasoning through a
story and really llms are just not up to
that task you know as it sits today and
as as it looks even in the near future
next slide
please but but that doesn't mean that
LMS couldn't still be useful so um uh
the combination of llms and story graphs
or story graph fragments is potentially
useful and makes sense you know from
what's in the literature today and what
looks to be coming down the
pike so for example um uh as a user
starts to create a story graph and and
inputs text or spoken language into uh
into the system to create a story graph
fragment an LM might be very useful to
to help understand the the words of
those passages and to put them into a
proper story graph fragment that might
be one example U and another interesting
really interesting uh approach is to use
a graph a story graph as contextual
input to an llm so in in in theory llms
could digest graphical information and
use that to provide a context for the
query and uh LS might be useful for
example in transforming story graphs or
story graph fragments into natural
language to you know to to uh export a
written story of you know what the story
graph is
saying and um
uh several new more sophisticated
approaches are are being developed for
llm there's many of them uh some of them
are actually what I've just mentioned
using graphical information as input to
the llm that's that's one of the
approaches and another is um is uh
processing the outputs of the LM through
some kind of other program maybe a logic
program to enforce semantic constraints
and you can think of that actually as
tool Ed by llm so that's really an an
interesting possibility
too and there's there's many others and
these newer more sophisticated
approaches you know could be useful in
in many areas of cogar potentially but
nevertheless it still appears to me that
using a meaning representation as an
inter intermediary either as input to an
llm or as something that you know that
the llm is creating from uh textual text
or spoken language would seem to be the
most useful um and productive U path to
follow at this
point uh next
slide okay so now we've talked about
several uh possible meaning
representations uh graph-based and and
not graph-based well most well yeah
graph based and not graph based TTR is
not uh uh HP Theory with records is not
really graph based but potentially it
could be converted to
graphs um so now we get an an idea of
what's out there and um now the task is
so what is the cogar meaning
representation and I said in a in a one
of the early slides whatever that
meaning representation is it's fit for
purpose and then we talked about what
that purpose is you know be for for
example be readable by both humans and
computers and
facilitate analytical and inference
computations
Etc um so in the paper I offer a deera
of about 20 or so items roughly 20
items um that this you know that's these
are the things that we would want a
cogar u meaning representation to to to
do or to qualities that we would want it
to have and these seven that I list here
is just kind of a smattering out of that
that larger set of about 20 or so
um uh we would want the obviously would
we would want the graph to be readable
by humans and computers uh for inference
and Analysis and and for computational
reasons we I think we would want the
meaning representation to be
based uh it should be capable of
handling document length text stories of
very stories that contain varied
linguistic phenomena and there's a lot
of linguistic phenomena if you're if
you're trying if you really want to
understand natural language there's a
lot of linguistic phenomena to
understand and some of it is quite
challenging um I I give examples of that
kind of phenomena in the papers in the
two papers uh the story graph should be
reproducible in the sense that similar
stories should have similar
graphs um otherwise comparing graphs
would not be so meaningful you know
comparing two stories by comparing the
graphs wouldn't be very meaningful it
the system should be able to handle
metadata for example if I'm I'm typing
in a passage of text but I want to refer
to a table I input a table of data or
maybe a you know a figure or
something and the the the meeting
representation ought to be able to
handle that it ought to be be able to
handle fluid beliefs because we're not
creating a story that is static we're
creating a story that is that is live
and amenable and if if this happens to
be a group event that's going in rounds
I might change my story parts of it um
you know over the next hour or the next
day or
something um and it should also be able
to handle beliefs about beliefs right so
but uh in this story I'm telling you I
believe that such and such person is
acting the way they're acting because
they think that such and such is the
case uh so beliefs about beliefs uh you
know uh and non-symmetric information
like in the story I know
that JN is a murderer but my neighbor
doesn't know
that um and this the the meaning
representation has to handle uncertainty
in all its
forms uh in in particular uh uncertainty
about uh predictions so part of the the
inactive inference part of the cognitive
process is uh anticipation of what will
happen if um some action is taken or not
taken so these are predictions
anticipations of what will happen if
certain actions are taken and a story
stories in general will have predictions
in them that you know typically will
have predictions in them for example if
we uh if we
tax uh Rich wealthy people more the
economy will get better or will get
worse or you know something will happen
so stories often usually uh typically
have predictions in them and there's
uncertainty associated with those
predictions uncertainty even about what
the story is saying like I think I saw a
horse in my front yard but I'm not sure
and uh if it's a horse I really better
go close the gate to the Garden or you
know sue my neighbor for letting their
horse eat my corn or you know
whatever um so how so now suddenly you
know I I showed you the picture of the
AMR the little graph for a sentence and
I showed you the sto the graphs for two
senten put together Maxell John push
them now we're you can see that we're
talking about something much more
sophisticated here we're talking about
you know predictions and models model
you know the output of of of
probabilistic models and um we're
talking about beliefs about beliefs so
that so one could imagine a meaning
representation that maybe has multiple
layers to it uh a graph-based meaning
representation that has multiple nodes
and multiple layers and uh that that a
user should be able to zoom in to to
look at a particular part or zoom out so
there should be very you should be able
to have various views of this um meaning
representation uh and as you zoom maybe
as you zoom out the it should be
possible to kind of summarize what
you're looking at if you zoom out all
the way out of a story maybe you end up
with something like a similar to a
tagline to a movie like uh this is a
story
about uh how how once how a man who was
once a thief turns his life around and
it's you know he says it's possible for
anyone in his position to do so you know
maybe that's the overall meaning of the
story but then you can zoom in to the
different uh
details um you should also be able to
confer nodes and edges in this meaning
representation with with meaning so
maybe a group of nodes and edges really
represents say a bank uh you know a bank
uh has some complicated transactions
that occur within it and there's ports
to this Bank the bank that you know
people can uh put their savings money in
this bank or take out loans and various
things so you could imagine some kind of
compositional or you know
um set of nodes and edges that have
meaning in in and of themselves and are
also reusable so to make it really
useful if you if I want if if many of us
are telling stories about Banks well it
might be very useful to have some Bank
objects that we have in a library that
we can uh include in our story that
makes it much easier to construct the
story and uh ideally this uh whole
meaning representation would be
compositional in the in the category
sense right so in category Theory G of f
there's a there's a function or map f
and g uh mapping um and you apply one to
the results of the other that's called a
composition uh that and in category
theory that that composition preserves
algebraic structure and then there's
functors between categories that
preserve structure including the
composition of morphisms so you if if if
it's possible that sort of approach
should be uh could be used so that it it
makes sense when you link uh you know
computational events together in this
graph uh you can that the in a sense the
meaning is is is preserved or conveyed
through some series of computations and
Transformations and that's different
than just modularity modularity really
means just the ability to chain things
together so uh compositional is um is
you know
kind of a more
sophisticated setting and as I said um
this should be able to reuse objects to
make it really easy and fast to create
graphs for some particular story so
these are just a small selection of the
many deada that are listed in the paper
and we whatever the meaning
representation is you know it would be
really good if all or many of these
could be
fulfilled next slide
please so um I've already mentioned
category Theory applied category Theory
so just a few more thoughts on that um
it category Theory can be used to reduce
the complexity of a of a you know of a
system to understand the complexity of a
system and to work with the complexity
of a system to manage
complexity and compositionality is part
of
that uh uh and particular there's a it
is I think possible to use cets which is
you know an object from applied category
Theory as uh as property graphs for as
the basis of story
graphs so you know I've already showed
you graph pictures of you know like say
AMR of what kind of a simple simple
meaning representation might look like a
simple cogar meaning representation
might look like but that could be stored
under the hood as property graphs where
a node has very you know flexible
properties that can be attributed to it
and same with edges edges can have
properties and all of that could be
stored at could be really
uh constructed as cets uh C sets from
applied category Theory um and then
there's also functors for various kinds
of Transformations graph to graph graph
to text Transformations that pert that
kind of preserve meaning through the
Transformations uh I've mentioned
zooming in and zooming out in
summarization uh uh that as there's an
interesting paper uh where an applied
category approach has been used to take
a system a this in the chemical world
but a a system of a a systems Dynamic
model of of a of a of a situation and
then convert that into causal Loop
diagrams and caal Loop diagrams are kind
of a simplified version of A System's
Dynamic model and um caal Loop diagrams
are sort of more uh you know
approachable for the lay public and uh
but still convey some of the main
information that's that would be
contained in the system's Dynamic model
so that would be that offers kind of one
possibility of how you might zoom in and
out and summarize uh meaning for story
graphs and then there's also
mathematical models of group
interactions and belief sharing uh that
could be constructed using you know
Concepts like sheath and topos Theory
from from category Theory so that's
that's C the the application of category
Theory to the cogar um meaning
representation and and cogar
computational process processes I think
is a really rich area for for
exploration next slide
so given all of that uh in the paper I I
suggest maybe the best approach for a
meaning representation is to base the
meaning representation on the on the
tree structure the the discourse
representation tree structure and then
with TTR type three with records and
higher order disco as being also
potentially
interesting uh but uh if drts is is used
sort of as the as kind of the main idea
then it would still have to have
numerous extensions as per the deera so
layers compositionality and so forth um
and as also I think it might be useful
to use a categorial grammar like com
combinatory categorial grammar ccg and
that kind of grammar is for example
patterns in a language so uh you know
verb noun adjective noun big dog uh dog
runs you know those sort of patterns are
would be uh U contained in a categorial
grammar and then the system would
understand if you use those patterns the
system would better understand what what
it is you're trying to say so that's a
form of restriction of input user input
to a categorial grammar but uh it it
probably makes sense to do so to improve
the capacity of the system to understand
what is being said and if you were to
use some kind of pattern uh in text that
wasn't part of the categor of grammar
then the system could say I don't
understand what you're trying to tell me
can you rephrase that do you mean this
or do you mean this you know something
like
that and then one inference one
potential inference pipeline is to use a
categorial grammar create the story
graph and then send uh uh convert that
story into a logical forms like for
example suitable for for natural logic
and then send the results of that to a
proof assistance a proof assistant for a
fast
inference these are just some ideas but
uh at this point it looks like this this
approach might be uh the most productive
of of of the approaches that we've
discussed next
slide um so some research questions
um there I should say that this is a
this is a it looks like a long list but
this is a short list of all the possible
uh you
know uh toos and questions that could be
raised about uh about the cogar system
and about the cogar meaning
representation I mean there's there's
really all kinds of questions like uh
you know questions that don't have
anything to do with the meaning
representation per se like how do how do
you ensure that um the information being
shared is is you know not manipulated
how do you how do you um you know ensure
the quality of information that's that's
being submitted and discussed in in this
cogar setting uh what are the social
implications of this what are the legal
implications of this you know there's
how do you protect privacy of of you
know person's information and their
stories there's all kinds of big picture
questions like that and then there's
detailed questions that need to be
answered too by
you know how do you construct what is a
what is the meaning graph uh
representation what is the role of of U
of category Theory and developing this
system
um what kinds of
stories are going to be applied here
what are what are the categories of
stories uh so just looking at the second
bullet there you know maybe one early
step is just to create a uh or excuse me
the first bullet is just to create a
small set of very simple stories maybe
the stories are only you know a short
paragraph in size and those serve then
as the kind of uh you know proof of
concept or that as the as the as the
core of what the rest of the of the
Machinery is constructed on um so
perhaps that's a good start to generate
a small set of simple stories you could
even be like three or four or five
simple stories just to
start and then you using those simple
stories perhaps develop some kind of
simplistic meaning
representation perhaps building on the
discourse representation tree structures
you know convey these simple stories in
that representation and then maybe that
process is even done manually at first
not not in some automated fashion
automated fashion the automation would
come later as you as you know we get
more familiar from comfortable with the
approach approach and the chosen meaning
representation um uh as I mentioned
category Theory and in particular
algebraic Julia which is a software in
the Julia system uh that is aimed at uh
applied category Theory uh could be
useful there's various kinds of models
in algebraic J Julia that could be
useful uh explore cets as property
graphs for meaning representations
that's that's would be I think useful um
uh given a simple the next bullet given
a simple meaning representation explore
Version Control Systems for that how do
how how are we keeping track of edits to
stories so that they can so that we have
a history of edits and so that uh we can
construct a uh you know we can
regenerate a story from the various in
original inputs in the edits and then
how are stories uh stored what kind of
database is used for storage and recall
um what how do we zoom in and out of
stories uh and summarize meaning of when
you know when you zoom
out what kind of query language is used
for story graphs you have a graph and
you have various questions that you want
to uh ask about the graph for inference
what kind of how do you query a a story
graph how are llms used what role do
they have could they be used for
generating a story graph fragment from a
a small text Passage
um what is the initial simple inference
pipeline does it involve for example
natural uh um natural logic and and uh
and proof uh
software proof assistance
um uh how about a simple analysis on
story graphs how do you compare the
similarity between two story
graphs uh maybe how do you what is the
first simple probabilistic model for
handling story graph uncertainty and
predictions how does that occur you know
there's various software U programs that
handle a probabilistic models so you
know choosing one of them and um
and you know incorporating uncertainty
and uncertainty really means too you
know in predictions maybe the future
comes out this way maybe the you know
and this this time I run the story I
execute the story computationally the
result is that you know events A and B
happen and then I execute the story
again and because it's a probabilistic
story events A and B don't happen in the
second round they they happen in the
some other event happens event C happens
then I run the story again and again A
and B happen and I run the story again
and again C happens and then I run the
story again and now D happens so uh you
know the outcomes of a story are are
variable because stories are
probabilistic that's the way we
understand the
world so all of those are research
questions to uh to consider uh ideas for
um uh moving forward ideas for getting
involved next slide
please and uh that's really kind of uh
where we're at right now we have a in
the series of papers I've laid out the
ideas of cogar sort of the vision of
cogar really um and that's all that's
been done on the cogar project to date
is these two papers there's there's no
there's no uh you know GitHub repository
for cogar code there's you nothing has
happened yet this is fresh I I hope that
the vision uh is interesting to not just
to other researchers but the public at
large and Civic organizations and people
who are interested in improving the
ability of society
to Cog functionally cognate and make
better decisions and um be functional in
the group setting uh so uh I I I hope
this project is of interest and uh cogar
really needs your help to move forward
um there's numerous interesting
questions to explore so please reach out
to me you know if you uh have
interest um upcoming uh I I I believe
that I'll be submitting a project to the
active inference Institute so that'll be
kind of one Hub to work through uh I'll
be involved in some additional talks the
active inference in Institute Symposium
coming up and so
on I think my email address is in the
papers so people can reach me that way
and or I think they can reach me through
the Institute and I I encourage uh any
who was interested to reach
out so that's what that's all I got
Daniel thank
you lot of places to uh continue for
people who are watching live feel free
to write a question how about just to
start it off what did you get more
curious about during the course of this
path oh well um you know
I obviously was a process to create
these papers and uh I I did you know at
first when I started I didn't realize
what I was up against I didn't realize
how complicated this project was and I
thought that I could I thought that I
could create a working model of you know
some code of a of a of a story graph and
doing inference on a story graph and
things like that and I suppose that
could still be possible but I realized
as I went through the process that there
were so many there was so much to uh you
know think about there was so much meat
to this whole thing that it would be
better for me to write two introductory
papers that lay out the vision than
actually constructing some initial
version of the cogn
system so you know that it was kind of
humbling and the process of humbling in
a sense in that I realized I really
didn't know enough to actually start
constructing the cogn system I really
needed to like lay out some of the
fundamentals before that step could even
be
taken yeah the the papers and the
presentation it's like a a whirlwind
tour of linguistics and
semantics you're dealing and invoking
with well you said like natural language
is ambiguous and then it's like well
what does that mean when it's precisely
what it is and then here's the vector
representation here's string diagrams
and all these different like proofs what
and all these interacting pieces like
the back end could have multiple
parallel or or related processing
methods one just doing like how many
words are there over under 300 words
defined by a space between the two words
and then some other part could could go
through llms it's like it's more like a
Linguistics Fusion approach and also
you're really focusing in on the
representation not so much on the the
social process around how people would
convene and narrativize around what it
is right right right that's a that's a
good point the the papers really are
focused on sort of the nuts and bolts
parts of this but clearly there would be
a large if if cogar were to be
successful there would be a very large
uh potentially large social impact and
then there would be all kinds of
questions some of which I already raised
about you know how do you protect user
privacy and how do you how do you ensure
that the you know quality information is
being shared and discussed you know all
that kind of stuff um so my thinking is
is that uh really I think maybe it's
better to focus on the nuts and bolts
Parts first to get a simple uh you know
to get
simple meaning representations
constructed you know convey a few simple
stories in them figure out some of the
inference methods that might work best
for this those kinds of nuts and bolts
questions and then once you have
something to kind of show and tell once
you have a little small working model
then start to explore you know how this
how you use this in the social setting
how do you how do you engage people to
participate in cogar you know how does
that work and and even there I imagine
the process that'll happen if if the pro
if the project moves forward is that
there'll be you know maybe the initial
work on this will be of slow and
detailed but uh as things as artifacts
start to be developed and there's you
know starts to be something to kind of
put you you know something you can hold
in your hand then there'll be a little
Wider Circle of researchers and you know
others from the Civic Society uh and
just ordinary people who become
interested in the project and start to
contribute and as that grows eventually
they be a you know start to be a little
bit more of a critical mass that oh this
is really starting to be a thing we have
you know there's we're starting to get a
repository for this we're starting to
understand how it could be used what it
would look like how we engage people how
how how we make this you know you uh
easy to construct stories story graphs
out of stories how you know how we
ensure that this the dialogue and the
and the discussions and the sharing you
know are healthy and and uh useful for
cognition and and and also also numerous
questions you know as that happens you
know there'll be more more and more of
the social questions will come into play
but there's also like all kinds of other
questions like how do you like in in the
nli setting it's really uh
straightforward how you measure success
you know you you you have a fixed set of
sentences you know you know this is
they're gold standard so you know what
the actual meaning of these sentences is
and then you score the model or system
that you're constructing on how well
they reach the actual meaning of these
sentences well they convey the actual
meaning well how do you do that in the
the cogar setting like how would you
actually do a study to prove that the
cogar system is understanding properly
what you're saying it becomes a little
more complicated because now you're
engaging the user in creating the story
in an interactive fashion so it's a you
know even studying the cogar system you
know from a scientific standpoint
becomes a little bit more complex right
because users are actively engaged in in
the
Dynamics and and for that matter you
know how do you how do you how do you
assess the quality of cognition that's a
really interesting question I've in one
of the slides I early slides I suggested
that active inference can be used as a
means to assess what functional
cognition looks like versus
dysfunctional cognition and and maybe
you can think just off the top of your
head of a few a few kind of examples
where that would clearly be
dysfunctional you know symptom of
dysfunctional cognition for example if I
had a pattern if I if I as a as a person
if I have a pattern
of of making really poor predictions
about what's going to happen next um uh
you know I see a a lion in the in the
road and I think oh that's a pet lion
I'll walk up to it and pet it on the
head that's a really poor prediction
right so that's a those kind of a
pattern of poor predictions might be a
sign of dysfunctional cognition well
what is that how do you assess
functional versus dysfunctional
cognition in this group setting right
there's many interesting appro Avenues
to just in that question alone many
interesting Avenues to explore
um uh for example the brain seems to uh
you know information flow in the human
brain seems to occur at that edge of
chaos concept you know it's it's not
it's stable the system is stable but
almost unstable and because it's almost
unstable potentially an input from off
to the side an in intuition from off to
the side can rapidly change the setup so
that I switch gears and now I realized
that that lion really is dangerous and
I'm going to uh you know jump out of the
way really fast so that a system on the
edge of chaos really is in many ways a
uh the most efficient processing system
you know it's most amenable to input
it's most flexible and yet it retains
its you know kind of core stability so
these
ideas ideas of chaos and other ideas
from complex system science could
actually be used for uh assessing
information flow in the cogn system and
and kind of the the quality of
information flow that's just one idea
but you know there's dozens of related
you know Avenues you could follow just
on that question
alone I'll ask a live chat question and
then anyone else write a live chat
question or I'll add anything if we have
time Andrew writes Dr Bo thank you for
presenting your work it's a very
interesting project do you have any
thoughts on implementation terms of code
EG any particular programming languages
or libraries
um well um I'm a I'm a fan of
Juliet so so in the papers I I I uh I uh
suggest various probabilistic software
programs and uh algebre Julia system
that I've already mentioned in this talk
uh Julia is fantastic uh for a variety
of reasons speed and other reasons now
that being said this project doesn't
have to be constructed in Julia but I
see I see Julia as a potential resource
for constructing this and and um maybe
as a place to start you know
initially you know
certainly Julie is an open source
project so as python but um you would
want to engage the open source community
and as much as possible in this project
because there's you know around the
world there's just so much talent and so
you know so many good ideas can come
from that um from that
world just on that topic on that topic
maybe this is kind of a an aside but um
this is this is conceived to be an open
source project and one of the reasons I
conceive it to be that way is um you
could imagine suppose that cogar was
successful and suppose that you had a
repository of stories and again each
story is conveying the belief system of
a human in relation to some
situation suppose you had a repository
of a million stories you have this
really rich information about how people
think you know in in different
situations in a variety of different
situations and um that kind of
information is very powerful very
powerful and you would not necessarily
want some private entity so you know
like a corporate entity to have control
over that whole thing I think you would
really want some kind of you know open
governance you know an open source
project controlled by some
governance uh uh you know framework is
to ensure that this whole thing is used
for the common good that it's really
used for purpose for its purpose
intended purpose which is to facilitate
a group cognition
a a comment in the chat sasia wrote Life
is thriving on the edge of Chaos and
Order so it's this kind of paradox and
the the precarious nature of the body
like how much oxygen storage does the
body have very little how much water how
much nutrition like there's different
kinds of reservoirs but it isn't just
trying to hold on to flows so that gives
a streamline
nature adaptive and on on the critical
Frontier and then at the same time also
precarious over different time skilles
and this is making it explicit with the
narrative and cognitive
infrastructure as the information
processing semantic linguistic narrative
elements of our ecosystem become like
more and more intermedia of more and
more active more and more
powerful yeah yeah you know as an
offshoot to that
comment
um I I I I I think that democracy the
idea of democracy could be framed in
that edge of chaos uh uh you know
view in the sense that in a democracy
what you would really like is that each
person has the potential to influence
the the group as a whole this you know
the condition of the group as a whole
and that's that's what that edge of
chaos you know allows because it allow
it's it's it's as I said before this a
system is stable but just on the edge of
of of maximal
flexibility so that an input from some
person like a you know an an IDE an idea
comment you know in a democratic system
can actually change the system you know
or or a group of a small group group of
people can actually change the system
with some good input so I think that uh
you know Not only was is that edge of
chaos model may be useful for cogar but
it might actually be useful as we
explore you
know the the interplay between you know
what is a political system what really
even what is an economic system what is
a political system what is an economic
system what is a legal system in the
context of the goal of group cognition
either societal cognition or
otherwise yeah another I think really
important point with the Jos you made of
graph-based more formalized non-d
distributional semantics and using llms
like to project onto those formal
structures generate from them first off
how incredible that from a semantic
graph we could generate materials in
many natural languages many lengths to
many different audiences if only for
starting points so just on the
generation side that's that's very
powerful and then an interesting thing
to consider is like the information
supply chain for example for someone's
voice in a group so then if People's
inputs are taken as a blob of text
smashed into a very large model and then
it comes out then the information supply
chain of that perspective has been
collided with a very large billions of
parameters lot of tokens of training and
then the supply chain of the resulting
outcome is like group perspectives
provided and whatever the question mark
unknown training and inputs supply chain
that are obscured for a proprietary llm
or even if it's an open source totally
open LM you'd still have a complex
information supply chain so this opens
up an opportunity for end to end
or in early stages or later stages or
parallel stages to be able to have the
kind of for example counterfactual
reasoning like here's how this graph
looked with and without here's the
distribution of outcomes with and
without what this traceback had done and
then there's kind of a a trade-off if
there's a more simple more symbolic
system like more Cod like more formal
semantic then the traceability will be
deeper explainability yeah and then if
you make it more statistical it'll start
getting blurred in with more and more
other factors just probabilistically but
it still could be disentangled so it's
like the llm route has the fluency and a
lot of other
advantages and and strengths and then
also having more traceable like rails
and flesh in in tandem could give it's
just a design palette it's not that one
or the other or the blend or it's
situational but using the two together
good point you you actually raise
numerous good issues there that are
worthy of you know prolonged discussion
but um one of the points you rais and
it's a really good point is that there
isn't just one model in in cogar to you
know to digest information from a group
of stories and present it to the group
as a summary that's not just a single
model doing that there can be many
different views many different questions
many different queries you can just like
uh you know just like the in like how do
you summarize the information about a
nation well there's all kinds of you
know ways to do that there's graphs
about the economy there's graphs about
health there's gra you know like there's
there's many ways to to to put together
the information from a from a body of
information to make sense of it and
cogar would you know most likely would
be multi models some some of which would
be maybe more explainable than other
models maybe you know some logic models
might be very explainable some results
of llm models might be less explainable
but nevertheless there would be a uh a
history of you know edits to story
graphs a history of how story graphs
evolved there would be there would be
the possibility of looking backwards in
retrospect to uh assess how the
evolution happened how what how ideas
developed uh you know how different
models might you know might have looked
at that information differently then you
can assess you could assess the the the
capability of cogar in retrospect about
how it how it handled various situations
you could assess the functionality of
the group process like was this
functional cognition were did did were
many voices heard was that information
used did was it did it represent
anything on the edge of chaos where you
know a single voice could have an
influence over the
whole you know um the the the U the
uh you know because there's a history
say you could examine that trajectory in
in in various ways and you know assess
your system and assess the group process
one interesting side inter point1 to
point two discussion was around like
classical and Quantum information
fungible and non-fungible information
and how like the single source of truth
that you invoked last time even though
that's a fractal concept just this get
Branch as its own sort of time cone of
of traceability of classical information
there are certain operations that you
can do like the diff the merge the
rebase and all those kinds of different
decisions however the actual
non-fungible cognitive
entities it doesn't work like that so
it's this interesting tension between
how enabled on certain Dimensions these
representations are but of course those
are not the first person perspective on
semantics the whole point of of the
second paper is to to throw some
approaches to this question of what can
you make that represents some Antics but
then immediately to whom SL how and and
they do they they represent and are
different things to different views like
for example just the visual view of a
figure and then the more statistical
analysis on the graph that is that the
same semantics is that different
semantics even though it's like the same
representation and so how does the
representation do relevant work in a
specific cognitive ecosystem and not
sort of like the systems design and the
metacognitive engineering question
especially if not too strong of even
though this is hard to to peel back to
but what what biases and what priors and
what biases and those are those are the
same
distribution right and and clearly the
system would have to be very transparent
to be able to you know assess all of
that to assess biases in the system to
assess bias in you know the way cogar
assesses similarity between stories or
something like
that so there's there's certainly a lot
to unpack with that I I do want to just
to briefly mention something that we
talked about in the first uh talk and
that is just to emphasize that um you
know we've been talking about uh groups
forming to you know explore some topic
that or situation of interest to them
cogar actually has a wide range of use
cases some of which don't look like that
at all cogar could be used for example
in customer service for a corporation
where people um or maybe submitting a
story graph to explain why their Gadget
broke or didn't work or you know why why
it broke or how it broke or whatever so
there's really a wide range of use cases
for this and secondly uh as I conceive
of cogar it's uh it's a tic to what the
group how the group wants to operate
right so uh it's not forcing a group to
use you know if say it's engaged a group
is engaged in decision-making is not
forcing a group to use majority uh you
know you know in voting use majority
rules or or rank Choice voting or some
other system of voting or some other you
know arrangement of how the group is
structured you know whether it's an
autocratic group or a Democratic group
or whatever
the cogar is intended to be kind of
agnostic to the group setting and so
that means that there's a variety of
types of groups with different interests
and different structures and different
rules and different methods and
different approaches can all use cogar
in the way that they see fit you
know there obviously might be some
restrictions on how it's used but by and
large it's flexible and and a kind of an
open system so that a so that you
know various kinds of groups can use it
for various
purposes but whatever you know the the
the system is whatever group uses it for
whatever purpose the the system is
learning from the engagement the system
is you know the com backend
computational system is learning you
know how people think what they what
they what they think will happen next
when this and that happens how how
better to con how better to summarize
information or you know present
information or encourage a group to move
towards well supported decisions when
they're trying to make decisions or you
know like all of that kind of stuff the
system is learning in the background you
know uh just like a an intelligent agent
would learn in a in a new
setting cool so maybe just what are some
of the possible
anticipated milestones for the rest of
the year
oh um I I most likely will try to these
are these two papers are in pre-print so
I most likely will try to um submit them
to journals for publication although
they are um kind of conceptual papers
they're they're you know not the normal
type of research
paper con they're concept papers uh uh
so that'll happen um I'll start that uh
uh a group a project at the uh active
inference Institute and I encourage
people to reach out to me on that um and
really will kind of I I hope to pick one
or two of these research questions
myself and focus on that next and so
hopefully there'll be a couple of more
papers coming out at some point here and
um you know really it's up to the
community as to what happens from there
I I'll do what I can and if people like
the idea maybe someone will jump in and
you know
participate and and maybe just in
closing we're almost done now at the end
of these two sessions and maybe it's a
would be just a good idea to kind of
look at the big picture a little bit as
to like why are we doing why is this of
any interest in anyone right it's an
interesting academic Excursion for for
certain there's all kinds of you know
basically touches on on numerous
scientific Fields so there's all kinds
of good research questions but why
should we even do this you know
and uh to that I would say there is a
you know at least I'm I'm proposing that
um groups can be thought of as organisms
cognitive organisms and as cognitive
organisms groups you know whether
they're Societies or corporations or
Civic clubs or whatever um need to be
able to be functional like make good
decisions to act in the way that AC of
inference kind of lays out in that the
you know functional group is going to
reduce the uncertainty about achieving
the kinds of conditions that are good
for it you certainly would want that for
society and you would even want it for
human civilization as a whole right it
would be good if
humans it reduce the uncertainty that we
live in a the a good kind of world that
people flourish in right we would want
that for everybody and um when you look
around today there's obviously
uh many many examples of what appear to
be poor decision-making on the part of
humans because we face really a poly
crisis climate change and and uh ex
Extinction rates are skyrocketing and um
we are in danger humans are in danger
serious danger and um new ways of of
looking at our situation our condition I
think are needed
in order to maybe steer a different
direction to inspire a different kind of
organization for society that is more
functional that that does exactly what a
functional organism does it senses its
World it makes decisions that are good
for it that reduce the uncertainty about
achieving the conditions that it needs
to thrive and
continue and I think that a
highlevel approach to uh the to you know
small groups large groups societies
holds great promise great potential to
to suggest ways that where we might not
be doing well and where we could do
better and and opens up a whole host of
really I think useful questions about
how could humans humans groups whether
we're talking about small human groups
or nations and civilization as a whole
how can we reorganize ourselves to
achieve what we actually want but to
function you know purposefully ACC fit
through through organizations and
institutions and rules and mechanisms
that are fit for
purpose that actually are quality
functional processes through which we
can sense our
world uh you knowe anticipate what's
going to happen next make good decisions
and reduce the uncertainty that our
future conditions are really what
exactly we need to thrive okay so
there's there's there's nitty-gritty
detail to this project that that are
important and interesting uh and then
there's this big picture that I think is
really really useful to to think of you
know uh of of how how viewing groups as
organisms that are cognitive and that
cognition has a
purpose functional cognition can be you
know uh described and used as a target
for moving human groups towards a future
where we are simply more functional and
I and I suspect that through the process
of evolution each of us or most of us
Crave You know are missing that maybe we
don't even know what we're missing but
were but once you get a whiff of what we
what functional cognition and good
decision-making and and fairness and all
that other kind of you know things that
go with it once that what what once you
get a whiff of what that feels like I
suspect that there would be a great
sense of relief you know for people they
would go like oh God I I'm so glad we
you know we can get together as a group
and be functional and make you know good
decisions and we have a we have some
clue as to how to assess the quality of
our interactions and our in our Cog
cognitive process so that we we know
that we're aiming towards a future that
is really substantially better than the
poly crisis that we now exist
in all
right thank you
John great times thanks for having
thanks for having me yep okay thanks
everybody in live chats too thank you
e e